Guide to the Frederick E. (Frederick Edward) Brasch Papers, 1745-1963
Department of Special Collections
- Thomas Jefferson Jackson See (Navy astronomer) (Box 26)
  - b) correspondence btwn T.J.J. See and John Nelson Stockwell (astronomer, 1832-1920) apparently re: See's proposed biography of Stockwell. correspondence continues after latter's death with other Stockwell family members (E.A. and J.W.) re: the project, copy of finished product: Histories Notice of John Nelson Stockwell of Cleveland (192-)
  - a) Misc. clippings re: T.J.J. See & the Naval Observatory at Mare Island. (Box-folder B26, F2)
  - b) Certificate given to See by the Accademia di Scienze Lettere ed Arti de'Zelanti, 1915.
  - a) T.J.J. See draft of biographical notice of J.N. Stockwell. (Box-folder B26, F3)
  - b) article re: an eclipse by Stockwell.
  - a) clippings re: T.J.J. See (Box-folder B26, F4)
  - b) photo of Newton medal awarded to See
  - Portraits of T.J.J. See (Box-folder B26, F5)
  - a) TLS (8 Sept 1942)T.J.J. See to a Navy admiral requesting assignment to special post as an advisor in science for Navy General Board. (Box-folder B26, F6-7)
  - b) T.J.J. See notes (AMs) on Cosmical mechanics
  - c) TLS (18 Feb 1931)TJJ See to Prof. Adams, director of Mt. Wilson Observatory, re: See's challenge to Einstein's theory of relativity
  - d) T.J.J. See drafts of comet study
- T.J.J. See: printed articles (Box 27)
  - Reprints of T.J.J. See article series, New Theory of the Aether., 8 papers, all present in at least one copy except #5. (Box-folder B27, F1-2)
  - Bound edition of the above. (Box-folder B27, F3)
  - Reprints of various T.J.J. See articles re: astronomy (Box-folder B27, F4-6)
- T.J.J. See: printed articles (Box 28)
  (Not divided into folders)
  Misc. reprints of T.J.J. See articles.
- T.J.J. See (Box 29)
  - a) Brief Biographical Notice of T.J.J. See (TMs) (Box-folder B29, F1)
  - b) T.J.J. See exams (AMs) from Navy training.
  - c) List of published papers by T.J.J. See (1889-1902).
  - T. J. J. See article drafts (TMs) (Box-folder B29, F2)
  - T. J. J. See biographical matter (Box-folder B29, F3)
    Photo of T. J. J. See
    Webb, W. L. Brief Biography & Popular Account of the Unparalleled Discoveries of T. J. J. See
    moon crater photos
    assorted charts.
    photos of scientists
  - Photographic history of T.J.J., See & family (Box-folder B29, F4-7)
- T. J. J. See: photos Framed photos (or prints) of:, (flat box) (Box 30)
  David Starv Jordon (original photo)
  Ben Franklin (print)
  S. Newcomb (print)
- T. J. J. See: photos, (flat box) (Box 31)
  - photos, prints, maps, charts of geological phenomena (Box-folder B31, F1)
  - Photos & prints of astronomical equipment & phenomena. (Box-folder B31, F2-4)
  - Photos & prints of scientists, including: Charles Darwin, Champ Clark, George H. Darwin, * J. N. Stockwell (1868),Cadwallader Coldon, William Herschel, Isaac Barrow, Edmond Halley, A. A. Michelson, various See family members., (many unidentified photos). (Box-folder B31, F5)
  - Photos continued: * Richard Brayar, * Stanford graduates of 1900, * Addie L. Hamilton & Bertha Mary shaw (class of 1901), Cornelius Bol, Franklin Wolff, Edwin Hubble, Léon Foucault, Isaac Newton Frederick E. Wright, Ainsworth R. Spoffor, (many unidentified photos). (Box-folder B31, F6)
  - Prints of Copernicus (Box-folder B31, F7)
  - Prints of science-related works of art. (Box-folder B31, F8)
- T.J.J. See: printed articles (Box 32)
  - Reprints of T.J.J. See astronomy articles (Box-folder B32, F1-3)
- Letters to T.J.J. See re: Webb's biography (see B29-F3) (Box 33, Box-folder B33, F1-4)
- T.J.J. See & Kenneth Albert (Box 34)
  This box contains See's correspondence re: Kenneth Albert (a.k.a., Havold Albin), an ex-naryman, sentenced to 15 years at Sam Quentin for his part in an escape attempt (Sept. 5, 1920). on July 1924, Albert began corresponding co/ See, his choice as advocate for an amnesty. The correspondence continued regularly for two years, ultimately leading to Albert's release. Included are letters from Brent A. Lindsay (See's legal advisor) and the Dept. of The Navy.
  Chronologically arranged.
  - Record of court martial proceeding (TMs) re: Kenneth Albert. (Box-folder B34, F1)
  - correspondence: 1924 (Box-folder B34, F2-3)
  - correspondence: 1925 (Box-folder B34, F4-5)
  - correspondence: 1926 (Box-folder B34, F6-7)
- T.J.J. See: correspondence (Box 35)
  - correspondence from See to W. L. Webb, author of Brief Biography & Popular Account of the Unparalleled Discoveries of T.J.J. See. Autumn 1913 - Summer 1914. (Box-folder B35, F1-6)
- Lick Observatory (Box 36)
  - Pamphlet, magazine descriptions & histories of Lick Observatory (Box-folder B36, F1-3)
  - Newspaper clippings re: Lick Obs. (Box-folder B36, F4)
  - Publications & programs of the Astronomical Society of the Pacific (centered at Lick Obs.,) (Box-folder B36, F5)
- Lick Observatory (Box 37)
  - Photos & printed matter re: Lick Obs. astronomer (Box-folder B37, F1)
  - a) Photos of Lick Obs. (Box-folder B37, F2)
  - b) Astronomical photos
  - a) Publications re: Lick Obs. (Box-folder B37, F3)
  - b) Publications by Lick Obs. astronomers
  - Matter re: American Astronomical Society (Box-folder B37, F4)
  - FEB drafts (TMs) of A Phantasy: Isaac Newton's visit to Lick Observatory (the City of Seven Domes). (Box-folder B37, F5)
  - FEB correspondence re: Lick Obs. and its astronomers. (Box-folder B37, F6-7)
- Lick Observatory (Box 38)
  - FEB correspondence with Nicholas u. Mayall, Lick Obs. astronomer. Also articles by, and newspaper clippings about, Mayall. (Box-folder B38, F1)
  - Ditto re: Charles Donald Shane, Lick Obs. astronome (Box-folder B38, F2-3)
  - Ditto re: Joel Stebbins, Lick Obs. astronomer (Box-folder B38, F4)
  - Ditto re: Ferdinand J. Neubauer, Lick Obs. astronomer (Box-folder B38, F5)
  - Brief biographical sketches and obituaries re: Lick Obs. astronomers (Box-folder B38, F6)
  - Pamphlets re: other observatories (Box-folder B38, F7)
- FEB and contemporary science (Box 39)
  - Misc. FEB notes (AMs) and articles re: astronom (Box-folder B39, F1-2)
  - FEB notes, articles, photos re: spiral nubulae (Box-folder B39, F3)
  - Matter re: the Nantucket Maria Mitchell Assn (Box-folder B39, F4)
  - Photos of Scientists, including: George Sarton, Henry Lerew, R.C. Archibald, Edgar F. Smith, Charles Albert Brown, W. Carl Rufus, George Ellery Hale, (others not identified) (Box-folder B39, F5)
  - Matter re: George Ellery Hale (1868-1938), American scientist (Box-folder B39, F6)
    obituaries
  - Misc. scientist photos, contemporary & historical. (Box-folder B39, F7)
  - Matter re: William Bond & the chronometer (Box-folder B39, F8)
    Includes letter (ALS.) to Dreyer from Hans Carl Frederick Christian, Danish astronomer (c. 1880).
- FEB and contemporary science (Box 40)
  - Matter re: FEB's attempt to prepare a biographical sketch of Dr. John L. E. Dreyer, historian of astronomy (f 1926). (Box-folder B40, F1)
  - Matter re: quaternary celebration of Copernicus' death (1943).Particulary FEB's correspondence w/ various involved organizations (Box-folder B40, F2)
  - a) FEB correspondence with C. K. Bolton of the Library of Boston Atheneum (Box-folder B40, F3-4)
  - b) Matter re: FEB's showing of Newton art at Stanford Art Gallery (1950)
  - c) Clippings of Royce Brier articles re: Soviet Union
  - d) Bulletin of the Univ. of Minnesota
  - e) List of History of Science Society members
  - f) Misc. FEB notes
  - Note cards evidently used to describe scientific equipment in an exhibit (Box-folder B40, F5)
  - * Computation of the orbit of a comet, 1897by W. J. Hussey. (Box-folder B40, F6)
  - Misc. clippings re: modern scientific discoveries (Box-folder B40, F7)
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 41)
  - Journal articles re: the Royal Society (Box-folder B41, F1)
  - Drafts (TMs) of The Exponential Theory of Gravitation by A. J. Schneiderov. Correspondence btwn Schneiderov and FEB re: submission of article to the American Philosophical Society (Box-folder B41, F2-3)
  - Matter re: Sir Oliver Lodge, scientist (Box-folder B41, F4)
    newspaper clippings.
    articles by Lodge.
  - Matter re: Harry Elmer Parnes, scientist (Box-folder B41, F5)
  - Matter re: American Astronomical Society (Box-folder B41, F6)
    photo of members
    notes
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 42)
  - FEB drafts of reports presented to a History of Science Society meeting (1923.)Related journal articles. Correspondence with Society. (Box-folder B42, F1)
  - FEB correspondence with the Society re: his proposal for a scientific institute sponsored (Box-folder B42, F2)
  - Misc. articles re: history of Science (Box-folder B42, F3)
  - FEB notes, articles, & correspondence re: astronomical spirals (Box-folder B42, F4)
  - Dr. Wartensleben, A Basal Error in Chemical Practice (TMs). (Box-folder B42, F5)
  - Articles (TMs) (Box-folder B42, F6)
    Clark, A. H and L. F. The Background of the American Assn. for the Advancement of Science.
    Rufus, W. Carl. Atmospheric Pulsation of the Stars (1924) and Outline of the Exhibit regarding the Origin of a New Method of Attacking the cepheid problem.
  - a) Matter re: 1957Gravity Research Fndn. Awards for essays on gravity. (Box-folder B42, F7)
  - b) Correspondence & articles (TMss) on gravity
  - Matter re: International Astronomical Union (Box-folder B42, F8)
    1961 issues of IAU News Bulletin
    1961 issues of IAU information bulletins
    programs for various functions
  - Misc. matter re: modern astronomy (Box-folder B42, F9)
- FEB and Contemporary Science, (not divided into folders) (Box 43)
  - Matter re: American Assn. for the Advancement of Science (of which FEB was assistant secretary in the 1920's)
    reports
    correspondence
- FEB and Contemporary Science, (This material located in envelope in the FEB oversize box) (Box 44)
  - Papers of George k. Lawton (astronomer), including charts of orbit of satellites.
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 45)
  - Matter re: FEB's article, History Activities of the USSR Academy of Sciences During the Past Twenty-Five Years, Science 99 (1944) (Box-folder B45, F1)
    drafts
  - FEB notes articles re: history of Harvard (Box-folder B45, F2)
  - a) FEB book reviews (AMs) (Box-folder B45, F3)
    Percual Lowell: an After low
    Einstein the Searcher
    Watchers of the Sky
  - b) FEB notes (AMs)
    select bibliography for outline of science
    Copernicus address
  - FEB drafts (TMs): Sir William Herschel (1738-1822). (Box-folder B45, F4)
  - FEB drafts (AMS): (Box-folder B45, F5)
    Outline of Syllabus of Leatures in the History of Science (1910)
    Hegel's Philosophy of History
    An Outline of Modern Naturalistic though with Special Reference to the Philosophy of ernst Haechel.
  - FEB draft (AMs) of Wilhelm Ostwold, Scientist Philosopher (1911).also magazine articles other matter re: the same. (Box-folder B45, F6)
  - FEB studies (AMs) of the history of cosmogony (Box-folder B45, F7)
- FEB & Contemporary Science (Box 46)
  - Misc. science articles (reprints) re: (Box-folder B46, F1)
    early american science
    contemporary astronomical discoveries
    scientific progress in general
  - Stephen Alexander, Statement & exposition of Certain Harmonies of the Solar System (Washington, 1875) (Box-folder B46, F2)
  - Astronomical papers prepared for the use of the American Ephemeris & Nautical Almanac (Washington, 1912) (Box-folder B46, F3)
  - a) Obituaries re: Arthur Compton, physicist (Box-folder B46, F4)
  - b) Phi Beta kappa handbook
  - c) Clippings re: George Washington University
  - * a) Portrait of Denison Olmsted (1859) (Box-folder B46, F5)
  - * b) Address commemorating D. Olmstead (1852)
  - c) Misc., partial FEB notes
- FEB & Contemporary Science (Box 47)
  - Obituaries re: W.W. Rouse Ball, English Mathamatician (1850-1925) (Box-folder B47, F1)
  - Misc. astronomy article reprints by (Box-folder B47, F2)
    Edward S. Holden (1880's)
    W. Carl Rufus (1940's)
    Benjamin Apthorp Gould, Jr (1850)
  - Transactions of the American Mathematical Society, 1 (1900) (Box-folder B47, F3)
  - Matter re: Florian Cajori (astronomer), including article reprints re: Newton (Box-folder B47, F4)
- FEB & Contemporary Science (Box 48)
  - FEB drafts & correspondence re: his reviews of (Box-folder B48, F1-2)
    Noyes, Alfred. Watchers of the Sky (N.Y., 1922)
    Hale, G.E. The New Heavens (N.Y. 1922)
    Bailey, S.I. The History & Work of Harvard University, 1832-1927 (N.Y., 1931)
    Wolf, A. A History of Science, Technology, & Philosophy in the 18th Century (N.Y., 1936)
  - FEB notes & drafts (AMs) re: The Science Exhibit at the P.P.I. Exposition Illustrating the Progress of Science in the Last Decade. (Box-folder B48, F3)
  - FEB draft, of The History of Science & its bearing on Philosophy. (Box-folder B48, F4)
  - Matter re: a philosophy course: (Box-folder B48, F5)
    syllabus
    FEB lecture notes (AMS)
  - Matter re: FEB's statistical study, The present status of the Teaching of the History of Science in our Universities, Colleges & Technical Schools. (Box-folder B48, F6-10)
  - Matter re: George Washington University midwinter convocation, 1928 (Box-folder B48, F11)
    news clippings
    info. re: university president C. H. Marria
  - Misc. news clippings (Box-folder B48 F12)
- FEB & Contemporary Science (Box 49)
  - Matter re: FEB's Newton portfolio project (Box-folder B49, F1-2)
  - Matter re: display of FEB Newton collection at Stanford, 1962. (Box-folder B49, F3)
  - Matter re: the publication of Marco polo's travels in 1930's (Box-folder B49, F4-5)
  - Matter re: FEB's project involving a history of science mural (Box-folder B49, F6)
  - Matter re: Senate proposal for federal support of scientific research (Box-folder B49, F7)
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 50)
  - Matter re: FEB's study The Present status of the Teaching of history in Science... (see also B48, F6-10) (Box-folder B50, F1-2)
    catalogues
  - Matter re: proposal for an institute for history of science & civilization (Box-folder B50, F3)
  - Misc. matter re: History of Science Society (Box-folder B50, F4)
    projects
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 51)
  - a) Article photostats re: some Newton letters. (Box-folder B51, F1)
  - b) FEB, The Portrait Medals of Sir Isaac Newton
  - c) Reprint of Nature (1927)article series re: Newton
  - Reprints of 40 FEB articles & reviews, many in multiple copies. Broad range of topics in colonial and modern science (Box-folder B51, F2-6)
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 52)
  - Matter re: A.S. Eddington, astronomer. (Box-folder B52, F1-4)
    article reprints
  - a) Article re: Halley's comey (Box-folder B52, F5)
  - b) Robbins, Frank. The Radcliffe Observatory, Oxford.
  - Matter re: John Couch Adams, 19th cent. astrom (Box-folder B52, F6)
  - Ritehey, G. W. L'Evolution de l'astrophographie et les grands telescopes de l'avener (1929) (Box-folder B52, F7)
  - Misc. matter re: (Box-folder B52, F8)
    Samuel E. Morison
    Senator Harry F. Byrd
    Leon Campbell
    Philip Fox
  - a) The practical observing of variable stars (1918 pamphlet) (Box-folder B52, F9)
  - b) William & Mary Historical Magazine, 1896, 192-issues.
- FEB and Contemporary Science (Box 53)
  - Matter re: Sir James Jeans, astronomes (Box-folder B53, F1-4)
    reprints of articles
- FEB and Contemporary Science, (not divided into folders) (Box 54)
  Misc. issues of ISIS (science journal), 1948, 1949, 1961-3.
  Tijdschrift voor Economie, 3 (1960)
  Briggs, W.D. Dr. Flügel as a Scholar
  Kansan - Taloudellinen Aikakauskirja, 4 (1959)
  reprints of articles on English grammar, philology
- Card index: science & astronomy (Box 55)
- Card index: Science & astronomy (Box 56)
- Card index: library reference cards (Box 57)
- Card index: A - Z (Box BOXES 58-63)
- Card index: Brasch Collection (Box BOXES 64-69)
- Card index: drafts of FEB's proposed catalogues of Stanford Newton collection. (Box 70)
- Card index (Box 71)
- Card index (Box 72)
- FEB and the Library of Congress (Box 73)
  - Pamphlets & booklets re: LC (Box-folder B73, F1-2)
    library guides
    commemorations of librarians
    exhibit catalogues
  - Matter re: Harriet Wheeler Pierson, friend of FEB at LC: (Box-folder B73, F3)
    correspondence (HWP to FEB)
    HWP articles re: LC.
- FEB & the Library of Congress, (not divided into folders) (Box BOXES 74-76)
  - LC material (mid-1920s to mid-1940s):
    annual reports of Smith division
    misc. correspondence
    pamphlets & articles re: LC
    news clippings re: LC, esp. obituaries
    programs & invitations re: LC functions
  - * speech of Mr. Bell of Tennessee on the message of the President of the U.S. delivered in House of Representatives, Dec. 26, 1838., (Printed)
- Science Catalogues, (not divided into folders) (Box 77)
  History of science book catalogues
  Catalogues of Scientific equipments some of antiquarian interest:
  Amsler & Wirz, Illustrated Catalogue of Mathematical, Optical, & Philosophical Instruments. Philadelphia, 1855
  Jones, W. and S. A Catalogue of Optical, Mathematical, & Philosophical Instruments (London, 1838
- Newton collection bills (Box 78)
  - Bills for items acquired by FEB for Newton collection, Includes (Box-folder B78, F1-7)
    book orders
    correspondence with dealers
- FEB correspondence (Box 79)
  - a) correspondence from Leon Campbell (Box-folder B79, F1-2)
  - b) Pamphlets & articles re: American Assn. of Variable Star Observers (Leon Campbell, President)
  - Matter re: Carnegie Institute (Box-folder B79, F3-4)
    programs & invitations
  - correspondence with Edgar F. Smith (1854-192-) prof. of chemistry at Univ. of Penn. Also clippings & articles about EFS. (Box-folder B79, F5)
  - correspondence re: the Edgar F. Smith collection in the history of chemistry, primarily from Eva V. armstrong (collection curator) and D. Walter Taggart (also associated with the collection) (Box-folder B79 F6)
- FEB correspondence (Box 80)
  - correspondence (1909-30)with Florian Cajori, math. prof. at Colorado College & Berkeley. (Box-folder B80, F1-3)
  - correspondence (1921-1944)with Fernando Sanford, head of Stanford physics dept. (Box-folder B80, F4)
  - correspondence with medical doctors, including: (Box-folder B80, F5)
    Henry E. Sigerist (Johns Hopkins): 1931-5
    J.F. Fulton (Yale): 1933-45
    Harvey Cushing (Yale): 1924-35
  - a) correspondence (1946-54)with T.J.J. See (Box-folder B80, F6)
  - * b) Photo of J.N. Stockwell with a letter from E.A. Stockwell to T.J.J. See. (see B26, F1)
  - correspondence (1935-56)with William D. Morgan, amateur astronomer & friend of FEB (Box-folder B80, F7)
- FEB correspondence, (not divided into folders) (Box 81)
  - Corres. (1930s - 1950s)with George Sarton; editor of Isis.
  - Corres. (1920s - 1930s)with R.C. Archiba prof. at Brown Univ. and fellow member of the History of Science Society. (Box 82, Box-folder B82, F1)
  - Corres. (1920s - 1930s)with prof. Philip Fox, astronomer assoc. with Adler planetarium (Chicago). (Box-folder B82, F2)
  - Corres. with those whose surnames begin with letter N. (Box-folder B82, F3)
  - Corres. (1920s - 1940s)with Eugene F. MacPike member of History of Science Society. (Box-folder B82, F4)
  - Corres. (1940s - 1950s)with G. Findlay Shirras, prof. of economics, Univ. of Illinois. (Box-folder B82, F5)
- FEB correspondence (Box 83)
  - Drafts of FEB biographical sketch of W. (Box-folder B83, F1)
  - Corres. with W. Carl Rufus (Box-folder B83, F2)
  - Misc. FEB Corres. (Box-folder B83, F3)
- FEB correspondence (Box 84)
  Corres. (1920s) with Dr. William A. Lacy, Prof. at Northwestern Univ.
- FEB correspondence (Box 85)
  Corres. (1920s-1930s) with David Eugene Smith, Prof of mathematics at Columbia Univ.
- FEB correspondence (Box 86)
  Corres (1920s) with Charles Singer, Prof. of medieval history at Univ. of London.
- FEB correspondence (Box 87)
  Misc. Corres (all times) incl. formal invitations to various social events.
- FEB correspondence (Box 88)
  Personal corres (1950s) incl.:
  Christmas cards
  Unitarian Church matter
- FEB correspondence (Box 89)
  Personal corres. incl.:
  Corres. re: library positions, acquisition of science materials (1910s-1930s)
- FEB Correspondence (Box BOXES 90-91)
  Personal Corres. (all times)
- FEB correspondence (Box 92)
  - Corres. (1927-8) (Box-folder B92, F1)
  - Corres. (1931) (Box-folder B92, F2)
- FEB correspondence (Box 93)
  - Corres. (1938-41) (Box-folder B93, F1)
  - Corres. (1941) (Box-folder B93, F2)
- FEB correspondence (Box 94)
  - Corres. (1939-42) (Box-folder B94, F1)
  - Corres. (1939-45) (Box-folder B94, F2)
- FEB correspondence (Box 95)
  - Corres, (1910s-1940s) (Box-folder B95, F1)
  - Corres. (1910s-1920s) (Box-folder B95, F2)
  - Corres (1910s-1930s)with Lynn Thorndike historian at Columbia. (Box-folder B95, F3)
- FEB Memorabilia (Box 96)
  - Misc. memorabilia (Box-folder B96, F1-3)
  - Photos: (Box-folder B96, F4)
    FEB
    FEB's residences
    Scientific equipment
  - Memorabilia re: England (esp. postcards) (Box-folder B96, F5)
  - * correspondence (1863, 1865, 1905, 1910)found by FEB in various commentaries on Newton's (Box-folder B96, F6)
- FEB Memorabilia (Box 97)
  (envelope: see oversize box)
  photo of Parthenon
  prints of early Harvard
- College Catalogues: Harvard (Box 98)
  Various Harvard publications, incl.
  Harvard catalogues (1903, 1930, 1932, 1935)
  Annual Report of Harvard Univ. (1828-8)
  Addresses at the Inauguration of Charles William Eliot as President of Harvard College (Cambridge, 1869)
  alumni bulletins & Harvard graduate magazine
  clippings & articles re: Harvard
  matter re: Harvard pres, C. W. Eliot
- College Catalogues: William & Mary Univ. (Box 99)
  William & Mary catalogues (1895, 1837, 1909, 1926, 1928, 1932, 1935, 1950)
  Articles re: Virginia
  Univ. of Chicago catalogues
- Studies in English Literature & Philology (Box BOXES 100-102)
  Reprints of articles re:
  Tudor / Stuart literature
  English linguistics & Philology
  Science articles (e.g., Milton the Telescope)